<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chris</title>
    <link>/</link>
      <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Chris</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Chris</title>
      <link>/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Raven</title>
      <link>/project/raven/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/raven/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SpotiTool</title>
      <link>/project/spotitool/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/spotitool/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SyncStream</title>
      <link>/project/syncstream/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/syncstream/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ObstacleSlam</title>
      <link>/project/obstacle-slam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/obstacle-slam/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Co-op, internships and robots</title>
      <link>/post/coop-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/coop-story/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Wow, where do I start? This is going to be a long post.
It was my sophomore year at the University of Manitoba. The Computer Science department&amp;rsquo;s co-op program opens applications for every second-year student. I don&amp;rsquo;t know the exact number of people that applied, but there were over 200 students in the co-op info session. Only 50 were to be selected from all those 200+ students. Everyone was getting excited to apply. You can imagine kids that just became adults not long ago being excited about the possibilities of working for Google, Microsoft or even the recently opened Ubisoft office in Winnipeg and, of course, earning money, gaining independence, getting experience before graduating, making connections, etc. The &amp;ldquo;Hunger Games&amp;rdquo; began.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FaceTool</title>
      <link>/project/facebook-likes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/facebook-likes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crypto-Quidditch</title>
      <link>/project/crypto-quidditch/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/crypto-quidditch/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PianoPlayer</title>
      <link>/project/pianoplayer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/pianoplayer/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robot Magic and Music: Humanoid Application Challenge</title>
      <link>/competition/iros2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/competition/iros2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2019, we signed up to participate in the Humanoid Application Challenge from the international conference 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iros2019.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IROS 2019&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
The competition this year was about magic and music. The sky was the limit regarding what could be achieved. Still, it had to be highly technical, fun and a wowing experience for judges and spectators. Team Snobots has always participated in doing magic and has done very well, even winning a robot in a previous year. This time, because of the music addition and that most of the team members were musical in a way, we decided to take that route instead of magic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a previous competition, we managed to have our two robots share the same code. We were excited to make them play together with us as a human and robot band. Mario, one of our lab members and a drummer, made the motions for our big robot to play drums and&amp;hellip; oh my goodness, the result was the real magic for us. As soon as we saw it we knew we were ready, even if we didn&amp;rsquo;t know how to do the rest, but we were so energized and inspired. We posted our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hE4ZpEnaQtY&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Qualification video&lt;/a&gt; and people were impressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real challenge began. Music is hard to program as you need precision. Robots can be reasonably accurate, but they have some milliseconds as a margin of error, which can become messy after playing for some time. Adding an extra robot to the scene made it even harder. In the end, we figured it out: UDP signals between the two robots to &amp;ldquo;update&amp;rdquo; each other in which part of the song they are in, an algorithm to measure how long each motion took and make them faster or slower to account for inaccuracies and a timer/calculator for the bpm of the song and how long each motion would take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In between, I learned more about OpenCV, visual servoing, inverse kinematics, UDP connections, human-robot interaction and music theory. Not forgetting also how to be a good showman and interact with the robot through some text-to-speech.
For more information about my version of visual servoing you can take a look at my 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/chris-mega/PianoPlayer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Github repo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trip to Macau was very exciting and long. When we arrived, we had some hardware issues which got me nervous at the moment of performance. We decided to play two simple songs (excluding &amp;ldquo;sound checks&amp;rdquo; that will show off our work with visual servoing and inverse kinematics). One of our songs was in Cantonese, and as soon as we played it, a lot of people entered the room as it is also a very popular song in Macau and Hong Kong. It was really touching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, we got 2nd place among six teams! The prize was a hand sponsored by 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.seedrobotics.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Seed Robotics&lt;/a&gt;.
Here is a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sci.umanitoba.ca/news/um-computer-science-team-achieve-2nd-place-finish-in-prestigious-robotics-competition-overseas/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; of the show (I sometimes cringe at how nervous I was, but I still would do it all over again)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some solo videos of each part of the performance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Lp4dbFI_9yg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Oscar - Sound check &amp;ldquo;Billie Jean&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ioqXlPz_vdU&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Polaris - Sound check&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=982TSPjSlCA&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Snobots Band - Knocking on Heaven&amp;rsquo;s Door&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eJbvUqCcffI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Snobots Band - Glorious Years&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./iros2019.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dr. Meng Cheng Lau&lt;/em&gt; (Post Doc Fellow), &lt;em&gt;Chris Melendez&lt;/em&gt; (me)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mRNElPifuhc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;An interesting video highlight&lt;/a&gt; where my profesor talked for a bit&amp;hellip; and I got a cameo!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FIRA 2019 South Korea- Hurocup Kid Size</title>
      <link>/competition/fira2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/competition/fira2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After the success of 
&lt;a href=&#34;/competition/fira2018/&#34;&gt;2018&amp;rsquo;s competiton&lt;/a&gt;, we participated in 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://firaworldcup.org/past-events/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;FIRA 2019&lt;/a&gt; at Changwon, South Korea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a really great experience! I learned a lot this year. There were more teams and everybody improved comparing to last year, which made the competition harder. Teamwork and leadership were the skills that I definitely practiced more this year as I was now on charge of the kid-size side of the team. The principal challenge was the hardware side, in robotics your code may work, but there are more variables that may make tour program succesful or not like camera calibration, surface roughness, servos and expected target sizes. Also practiced how to change a servo in 10 minutes under pressure 😁&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We moved to a shared platform, which meant to handle two different robots using the same code and framework (&lt;strong&gt;Robotis-Op3-Framework&lt;/strong&gt; in ROS) while making it easier to compile by moving the events to Python. I was involved in the design of the architecture and tasks to reach our goals, in addition to the programming of some of the events. That meant more collaboration across the adult and kid size teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also improved in &lt;strong&gt;OpenCV&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Python&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;ROS&lt;/strong&gt; as after a year and a bit more guidance I could understand more of how everything works. This is our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ag4jiWB4jw0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;qualification video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As &lt;strong&gt;Kid-size&lt;/strong&gt; team, we achieved:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spartan Race&lt;/strong&gt; - 1st Place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;United Soccer&lt;/strong&gt; - 2nd Place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Triple Jump&lt;/strong&gt; - 3rd Place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Basketball&lt;/strong&gt; - 4th Place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marathon&lt;/strong&gt; - 5th Place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mini-DRC/Teleop&lt;/strong&gt; - 5th Place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All-round&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;em&gt;Fourth Place&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also got an article written by 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://news.umanitoba.ca/international-success-for-u-of-m-robot-team-at-fira-hurocup/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UManitoba press&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part of the Team:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./fira2019.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marshall Jackson&lt;/em&gt; (adult-size), &lt;em&gt;Borui Li&lt;/em&gt; (adult-size), &lt;em&gt;Yanlam Ng&lt;/em&gt; (adult-size), &lt;em&gt;Dr. Meng Cheng Lau&lt;/em&gt; (Post Doc Fellow), &lt;em&gt;Chris Melendez&lt;/em&gt; (me, kid-size), &lt;em&gt;Louis O&amp;rsquo;Connor&lt;/em&gt; (kid-size), &lt;em&gt;Andy Lun&lt;/em&gt; (adult-size)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FABRIK</title>
      <link>/project/fabrik/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/fabrik/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FIRA 2018 Taiwan - Hurocup Kid Size</title>
      <link>/competition/fira2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/competition/fira2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2018, I applied for an undergraduate research award. I had to write some essays about what I want to do in the future, what I am doing to accomplish it and how the labs at the university would be able to help. That&amp;rsquo;s when I came across the 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://aalab.cs.umanitoba.ca/index.php/9-news/70-fira-hurocup-2018&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Autonomous Agents Lab (AaLab)&lt;/a&gt;, Dr. John Anderson (Lab Director) and Dr. Meng Cheng &amp;ldquo;Mc&amp;rdquo; Lau (Post Doc Fellow). They showed me around the lab, the research they do and the competitions they have participated in. I got very excited to see the combination of hardware and software without knowing much about the hardware. I wrote my essays and got the award.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I could describe my first month in this lab with one word, it was: Total Confusion (oops, that&amp;rsquo;s two words). The lab just got a new robot as an award from a previous competition: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://emanual.robotis.com/docs/en/platform/op3/introduction/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Robotis OP3&lt;/a&gt;. So, I was assigned to the Kid-Size team (kid size because it is a small robot, a bit higher than your ankle) to figure out how it works and participate in the upcoming 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://firaworldcup.org/past-events/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;FIRA Hurocup 2018&lt;/a&gt;. No one knew exactly how to use it; other student volunteers with more experience had some ideas ported from the previous version, OP2, but the framework for OP3 is different, involving &lt;strong&gt;ROS Kinetic&lt;/strong&gt;, publishers and subscribers and &lt;strong&gt;C++&lt;/strong&gt;. Because I was getting paid by the award, I had times of being by myself there, trying to figure out how everything works and getting guidance on computer vision (&lt;strong&gt;OpenCV&lt;/strong&gt;) and movement animation. There were a lot of trials and errors, but it was very fun. Finally, we could make it work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, but also luckily, the most experienced guy quit, so it allowed me to travel instead with another Kid-Size guy and two adult-size guys to Taichung, Taiwan. This was our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GU-4sg2ITcE&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;qualification video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a lot of excitement! First time in Asia, representing Canada, seeing 3 months of work finally compete and getting to know people from all over the world. There were also some high expectations from us as &lt;strong&gt;Snobots&lt;/strong&gt; (our official team name) has performed very well in the past years. Now the competition had more teams, old teams got strong, new sporting events were added but both me and my kid-size partner were new on this kind of competition using a new robot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end, as &lt;strong&gt;Kid-size&lt;/strong&gt; team, we got:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weightlifting&lt;/strong&gt;- 2nd Place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Triple Jump&lt;/strong&gt; - 3rd Place (New Event)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moving Target Archery&lt;/strong&gt; - 4th Place (New Event)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Obstacle Run&lt;/strong&gt; - 5th Place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mini-DRC/Teleop&lt;/strong&gt; - 7th Place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All-round&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;em&gt;Fourth Place&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were actually really impressed to get 4th place all-round due to our experience. This taught me that it isn&amp;rsquo;t about knowledge, it is about persistence, focus, belief, handling stress, collaboration and teamwork.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this amazing experience, I decided to stay as volunteer for the Aalab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part of the Team:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./fira2018.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chris Melendez&lt;/em&gt; (me, kid-size), &lt;em&gt;Mario Mendez&lt;/em&gt; (adult-size), &lt;em&gt;Dr. Jackie Baltes&lt;/em&gt; (organizer), &lt;em&gt;Dr. Meng Cheng Lau&lt;/em&gt; (Post Doc Fellow), &lt;em&gt;Louis O&amp;rsquo;Connor&lt;/em&gt; (kid-size), &lt;em&gt;Borui Li&lt;/em&gt; (adult size)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XYiV4w-yaQI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;External highlights Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
